NYSUT Vice President's office files. 6174/002
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Task Force on School Violence 1999-2000 (Box 24, Folder 18)
  Task force report, "Safer Schools for the 21st Century," October 1999; draft report, with cover letter from Lieutenant Governor Mary O. Donohue, September 13, 1999; related correspondence, summary of recommendations, and press releases in reaction by NYSUT, NYS School Boards Association; draft sample annotated Code of Conduct, 11/6/00; Governor's Task Force on School Violence list of members of Prevention and Education Subcommittee, revised 7/01/99
- Task Force on School Violence. Prevention & Education Subcommittee July 1999 (Box 24, Folder 19)
  Agenda; outline of potential issues for review; draft recommendations, July 12, 1999; preliminary report, July 26, 1999; summary of other subcommittee reports
- Task Force on School Violence. Prevention & Education Subcommittee 6/30/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 20)
  List of members; description of state models; outline of potential issues for review; letter to Cortese from Commissioner of Education, describing agenda of meeting, June 17, 1999
- Task Force on School Violence 6/30/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 21)
  Press releases from Lieutenant Governor's office announcing legislation to increase penalties for violent crimes in schools; correspondence between NYSUT, State Education Department counsel, and Dutchess County District Attorney re police presence on school property
- Task Force on School Violence 5/10/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 22)
  Correspondence re public hearings
- Task Force on School Violence 4/27/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 23)
  Press releases from NYSUT and NYS Executive Chamber (Governor's and Lt. Governor's offices) re formation of Task Force on School Violence
- Task Force on School Violence 4/15/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 24)
  Press releases from Lt. Governor's office re formation of Task Force on School Violence; biographical sketches of task force members
- Governor's Conference on School Violence Prevention 3/5/99, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 25)
  Printed conference program; draft agenda
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on School Violence 1994-1995 (Box 24, Folder 26)
  Minutes of May 13, 1994, meeting; memo re implementation of 1994 Representative Assembly (RA) resolutions, February 2, 1995
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on School Violence. 5/13/94, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 27)
  "Report of the School Safety Department for the 1992-93 School Year," United Federation of Teachers (UFT); statistical charts re incidents of violence involving UFT members in NYC schools, 1992-93, and since 1976; resolutions referred to NYSUT Board of Directors recommending harsher penalties for juvenile violence; NYSUT Safe Schools Program for Local Leaders materials, including "Investigating Your School's Discipline Policy"; NYSUT-proposed Safe Schools legislation, increasing penalties for possession of weapons on school grounds, among other provisions
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on School Violence. 2/11/94, 1994 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  Agenda; minutes of January 7, 1994, meeting; NY State Education Department report, Violence in the Schools: A National, State, and Local Crisis, January 1994; list of proposed bills
- NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on School Violence. 1/7/94, 1994 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  Agenda; NYSUT report, "Fighting Violence in the Schools: A Summary of Applicable Law and Regulations," December 16, 1993; Colorado law on student discipline; NYC Board of Education action plan for school safety
- Sexual Harassment Committee 2/3/97, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  Agenda of February 2, 1997, and February 27, 1995, meetings; minutes of February 27, 1995, and November 2, 1993, meetings; memo from Hobart re update of policy, April 29, 1996
- Sexual Harassment Policy Committee 11/2/93, 1993 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  Agenda; NYSUT policy overview
- Task Force on Sexual Harassment 1991-1993 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  Memo to NYSUT president Hobart reporting on meeting of Governor's Task Force on Sexual Harassment, June 7, 1993; memo from Hobart to NYSUT managers re sexual harassment policy orientation program, November 18, 1991; outline of presentation at American Bar Association seminar on sexual harassment, September 30, 1991; Research institute of America Special Study: Sexual Harassment in the Workplace, July 1991
- Sexual Harassment Meeting 9/5/91, 1991 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  Memo and reference material
- Sexual Harassment (Management Meeting) 6/19/91 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  "Intent vs Impact: A Sexual Harassment Prevention Training Program," by BNA Communications, Inc., 1988; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Sexual Harassment Meeting 2/19/91 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  Memo re meeting
- Sexual Harassment (Training) 1/7/91, 1991 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  Memo re training session pre-training questionnaire, filled out by Cortese; article reprints; recommended NYSUT policy statement; sexual harassment disciplinary guidelines; handwritten notes
- Al Shanker. Memorial Service 3/24/97, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  Memorial programs
- Al Shanker's Column "Where We Stand" 1995-1997 (Box 25, Folder 11)
  Collection of columns and articles by and about Shanker
- Al Shanker. "Keep the Clock" 3/6/76, 1976 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  Address before the 4th Annual Representative Assembly
- Shanker Institute (AFT), Corporate Members Meeting, Feb. 5, 2004 (Box 25, Folder 13)
  Agenda of Albert Shanker Institute; minutes of corporate members meeting of May 28, 2003; draft document, "Rationale for a Shanker-Sponsored 'Center for Educating Democracy'"; draft Shanker Institute Five-Year Report, 1998-2003, "The Power of Ideas in Action"; bios of current board members
- Shanker Institute. Bridging the Gap Forum March 2002 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  Agenda and materials, "Bridging the Gap between State Standards and Classroom Achievement: The Challenge of Curriculum and Professional Development," March 20-21, 2002
- Shanker Inst., Study Trip, France 4/7-13/01, 2001 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  Description of pre-K in Albany district 1999-2000; list of "Education and Care for Children in Their Pre-School Years" seminar participants; facilitative materials re trip
- Shanker French Seminar 2/21/01, 2001 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  Correspondence
- Shanker Institute. Leadership 1998-2000 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  Publication, "Building a New Structure for School Leadership," by Richard F. Elmore, winter 2000; preliminary report by Task Force on the Albert Shanker Institute re mission of institute; memos and related papers re model leadership practices
- Shanker Institute, Seminar, Washington 9/21/99, 1999 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  Regents list of members of NYS Academy for Teaching and Learning; June 1998; agenda for seminar, "Teachers, Principals, and Standards: Workforce Development at the School Level"
- Shanker Inst. Task Force 10/14/97, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  Agenda; minutes of April 28 and July 3, 1997, meetings; mission statement; position paper re children ages 0-8; memos; handwritten notes
- (Shanker) AFT Institute Task Force 4/28/97, 1997 (Box 25, Folder 20)
  Agenda; memos re development of Shanker Institute
- Shared Decision Making. NYSUT Ad Hoc Task Force on Proposed Part 100 Revisions 10/20/98, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  Agenda; background information prepared for task force; State Education Department discussion paper re revision of Part 100 of the Regulations of the Commissioner, August 31, 1998. See also: Restructuring; See also: Part 100 Regulations; See also: Joint Decision Making
- Shared Decision Making. Proposed Changes to Regulations Part 100 1999 (Box 25, Folder 22)
  Statement of NYSUT on Proposed Changes to Commissioner's Regulations Part 100, Including Professional Development Plans and the Annual Professional Performance Review, February 12, 1999; text of draft regulations; interim NYSUT policy in response to proposed changes
- Shared Decision Making (Part 100.11. Teacher Participation) (folder 1) 1993-1994 (Box 25, Folder 23)
  NYSUT Information Bulletins re shared decision making; NYSUT "Compact for Learning" implementation plan; correspondence; handwritten notes
- Shared Decision Making (Part 100.11. Teacher Participation) (folder 2) 1992-1993 (Box 25, Folder 24)
  Questions and answers by NYSUT; Regents discussion papers on Commissioner's Regulations Part 100.11; NYSUT policy paper, "NYSUT's Pilot Project: A Policy Direction for Restructuring"
- Shared Decision Making (Part 100.11. Teacher Participation) (folder 3) 1994-1998 (Box 25, Folder 25)
  Survey Report on the Implementation of the New Compact for Learning by NYS Superintendents, April 8, 1994; letter to Cortese from NYS Council of School Superintendents (NYSCOSS), with attached position paper, "Assessing the Assessments," July 2003 by NYSCOSS Curriculum and Instruction Committee; packet of materials from Wheatland-Chili Federation of Teachers re problems with superintendents not wanting to comply with shared decision making with teachers, June 3, 1997; letter from NYSUT president Hobart to State Education Department, commenting on effectiveness of CR 100.11 in meeting goals of including parents, teachers, and administrators in decision making, February 20, 1998; appeal by president of Indian River Education Association to Commissioner re shared decision making, July 1994; scholarly article; request to local president from Cortese to evaluate whether shared decision making is working in their districts to improve student achievement, November 27, 1995; related correspondence
- Shared Decision Making Agreements 1992-1993 (Box 25, Folder 26)
  Draft or revised agreements with Royalton-Hartland Central School District, Wallkill Central School District; shared decision making handbooks by Fallsburg Central School District and Carmel Central School District; State Education Department questions and answers sheet re Commissioner's Regulations Part 100.11 in shared decision making, March 31, 1993
- Sick Building Syndrome NYSUT Findings 1993 (Box 25, Folder 27)
  Draft of press release, "NYSUT Finds Sick Building Syndrome Affects Many Schools and Colleges"; press release, "NYSUT Survey Shows School Buildings May Make People Sick"; UFT press release, "UFT Blasts Board and City for Deplorable High School Conditions"; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Skills Opportunity/Youth Centers 1990-1991 (Box 25, Folder 28)
  Internal NYSUT memos re proposed legislation for Skills Opportunity Centers for dropouts, including memo from Chuck Santelli to president Tom Hobart, suggesting discussion of other "serious proposals to deal with dropouts," including revocation of driver's licenses, mandatory military service, and mandatory work/student programs, January 8, 1991; text of proposed legislation. See also: Dropout Prevention; See also: School Attendance; See also: Children at Risk
- Sobol. See: Commissioner
- Social Promotion 1990-1997 (Box 25, Folder 29)
  Paper, "Fairness and Core Knowledge," E. D. Hirsch, Jr., 1991; selected highlights from NYSUT telephone survey of elementary school teachers on educational standards, February 1996; results of NYSUT survey of local presidents re social promotion, 1993-94; National Center for Restructuring Education, Schools, and Teaching (NCREST) Resources for Restructuring summer 1996 issue, "Alternatives to Grade Retention"; AFT report, "Passing on Failure: District Promotion Policies and Practices," September 1997, with cover letter noting related speech by AFT president Sandra Feldman to National Press Club, September 4, 1997. See also: Dropout Prevention; See also: Restructuring
- Social Security 1998-1999 (Box 25, Folder 30)
  Text of speech by NYSUT vp Toni Cortese on Social Security, at acceptance of NYS Council of Senior Citizens Intergenerational Award, n.d.; presentation on Social Security by David Smith, director, Public Policy Department, AFL-CIO, to the AFT Executive Council, February 8, 1999; testimony of Smith before the Senate Budget Committee on Social Security in the 21st Century, January 22, 1999; AFL-CIO Executive Council statement, "Principles for Social Security Reform," calling for budget surpluses to be used to restore Social Security funding, not tax cuts, opposing raising eligibility age or reducing benefits; August 5, 1998; outline of Clinton Social Security proposal, including personal retirement savings accounts; fact sheet by National Council of Senior Citizens; pro-Social Security booklet, "Agenda 2000: A Generational Perspective on America's Economic Progress," by the 2030 Center
- Soft Drinks. See: Pouring Rights
- South Africa Conference January 10-12, 1985 (Box 25, Folder 31)
  Information brochure on A. Philip Randolph, originally in New York Teacher, October 13, 1974; press releases from the A. Philip Randolph Institute and AFL-CIO re South Africa; NYSUT agenda for South Africa conference, January 8, 1985; agenda for Conference on South African Black and Non-Racial Unions; "Trade Unionism as a Force for Change in South Africa," sponsored by the A. Philip Randolph Educational Fund and African American Labor Center, January 10-12, 1985; statement of Ray Denison, director, Department of Legislation, AFL-CIO, to the Subcommittee on Africa of the House Committee of Foreign Affairs on H.R. 3597, concerning a ban on new U.S. investments in South Africa, and H.R. 3008 concerning fair employment codes in South Africa and curbs on financial practices, October 30, 1981; AFL-CIO Program of Action in Support of Black Trade Unions in South Africa, n.d.; statement by AFL-CIO Executive Council, Apartheid in South Africa, May 1, 1958
- South Africa Trip (folder 1 of 5) September 24-October 15, 1981 (Box 25, Folder 32)
  Materials from South African teachers unions; "A Proposal for the Formation of a Council for Black Education and Research, Resulting from the Meeting of the Undersigned Members of the Steering Committee Held on August 20 1979"; newspaper clippings, handwritten notes
- South Africa Trip (folder 2 of 5) September 24-October 15, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 33)
- South Africa Trip (folder 3 of 5) September 24-October 15, 1983 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  AFT report, "Teacher Organizing in South Africa: A Report and Some Proposals," May 12, 1982; Georgetown University International Labor Program paper, "Black Labor as a Swing Factor in South Africa's Evolution," by Roy Godson, spring 1979; Africa Fund (associated with the American Committee on Africa) paper, "Black Unions in South Africa," 1982 (?); unclassified 1980 Annual Labor Report to the U.S. Department of State from Amcongen Johannesburg, April 16, 1981
- South Africa Trip (folder 4 of 5) September 24-October 15, 1984 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  Trip report
- South Africa Trip (folder 5 of 5) September 24-October 15, 1985 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  Trip reports to South America
- Special Education 1997-1999 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  NYSUT Information Bulletins re changes to NYS Special Education Law, 1999; research/policy paper, "Possible Options for Cost Savings in Special Education Programs," February 25, 1997; related materials. See also: Mainstreaming
- Regents Forum on Special Education 9/29/04, 2004 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  NYUST talking points for Regents public forums; materials from State Education Department about forums
- Special Education: Educational Interpreters 2004 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  Letters to NYSUT vice president from State Education Department re certification of educational interpreters for deaf students
- Special Education News Clips 2004 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  Article re teachers' union request for investigation of Yonkers schools for staffing cutbacks affecting special education students
- Special Education Testimony 3/19/97 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  Testimony of Cortese to the NYS Assembly Committee on Education re Reform of Special Education Funding, March 19, 1997; description of Regents' proposal and governor's proposal; handwritten notes
- Special Education Costs 1992-1995 (Box 26, Folder 9)
  Memos re suggestions to cut costs in special education programs; NYSUT memo re placement of pre-school disabled students, June 20, 1995; letter from Cortese to State Education Department commenting on draft "New York State Plan for the Education of Children with Disabilities, 1996-1998" and "New York State Preschool Grant Program," October 28, 1994
- Special Education Classes 1991 (Box 26, Folder 10)
  Correspondence re visits by Regents to special education classes and information sessions for parents and teachers re new regulations on class size
- Special Education Committee 1991-1993 (Box 26, Folder 11)
  NYSUT Special Education Committee 1992-1994 end-of-term report; testimony by Cortese at public hearing of NYS Assembly Standing Committee on Education re issues affecting special education, February 12, 1993; NYSUT urgent action memo re reductions in special education programs under proposed new Commissioner's Regulations, calling on local presidents to lobby Regents, March 12, 1991; NYSUT resolution opposing cuts in services, n.d.; letter from Commissioner Sobol to Assembly Speaker Mel Miller re regulatory and legislative mandate relief (i.e., cost cutting) proposals, March 11, 1991
- Special Education 1985 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  Text of draft legislation developed by the NYS Assembly Task Force on Special Education, April 19, 1985; meeting agenda for NYSUT Special Education Committee, May 3-4, 1985; document, "Assorted Special Education Matters"; outline for NYSUT workshop, "Securing Pupil Services"
- (Special Education) Students with Disabilities. Discipline Procedures 2000-2001 (Box 26, Folder 13)
  Draft document explaining new Commissioner's Regulations re discipline procedures for students with disabilities, with cover letter to Cortese requesting comments, May 5, 2000; final document, with cover letter, January 29, 2001; response to Cortese re general policy recommendations re students with disabilities, April 2, 2001
- (Special Education) Success for All 1999-2000 (Box 26, Folder 14)
  Conference summary report; letter to Cortese from special education teachers at Jefferson School, New Rochelle, asking for NYSUT help, June 14, 2000
- (Special Education) Success for All 5/1/99, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 15)
  Conference agenda for program designed to increase reading skills of "at- risk urban children" and students otherwise developmentally disabled; press release
- (Special Education) Success for All 5/6/00, 2000 (Box 26, Folder 16)
  Conference agenda; handwritten notes
- Speeches 1996-2002 (Box 26, Folder 17)
  Outline and draft remarks for 1997 Representative Assembly speech by Cortese; outline of 1996 speech; memo re background research on standards, April 27, 1997; survey results of teacher opinions re rigor of Regents exams, 2001-02; teacher survey 1997; materials of Task Force on Time, 2002; opinion article by IBM chair Lou Gerstner, in New York Times, n.d; related Times article; article from U.S. Newswire comparing professional standards, status, and salaries for teachers in U.S. and eight developed countries, April 10, 2000; handwritten notes
- Speeches 1996-1997 (Box 26, Folder 18)
  Memo outlining key points from Linda Darling-Hammond's presentation at Inservice Conference, January 24, 1997; booklets prepared by NYSUT Legislative Department, "New York State Tax Cuts: Promise or Peril? Committee of 100," May 13-14, 1996, "Committee of 100," May 13-14, 1996; "Committee of 100," March 25-26, 1996
- Speeches 1978-1992 (Box 26, Folder 19)
  Outlines and handwritten notes on various speeches, including Western New York Leadership Conference; 1992 RA speech ("never delivered"); community services conference, June 3, 1991; many unidentified
- Speeches. Amsterdam Scholarship Award Dinner 6/4/98, 1998 (Box 26, Folder 20)
  Letter to Cortese from Fulton-Montgomery Teachers' Cluster (including Amsterdam Teachers' Association) re speaking at awards ceremony; handwritten notes outlining speech
- Speeches. Graduation Speeches. Gov. Cuomo 1986-1993 (Box 26, Folder 21)
  Text of remarks by Gov. Cuomo at graduations of Dalton School, 1987; Jamestown High School, 1986; International High School, 1988; Voorheesville High School, 1993; by Mrs. Cuomo, Ramapo High School
- Speeches. RA (Representative Assembly) Speech 2004 (Box 26, Folder 22)
  Text of speech
- Speeches. RA Speech 2003 (Box 26, Folder 23)
  Outline and draft of speech re No Child Left Behind; articles and other background materials, including NYSUT publication, "Don't Fail Us Now: New York: A State at Risk," April 2003, and Washington Times article criticizing the NEA
- Speeches. RA Speech 2002 (Box 26, Folder 24)
  Outline of speech; background materials re new standards-based assessments (Regents exams)
- Speeches. RA Speech 2000 (Box 26, Folder 25)
  Outline of speech; handwritten notes; background materials re teacher shortage projections
- Speeches. RA Speech 1999 (Box 26, Folder 26)
  Draft of speech for delivery April 22, 1999, welcoming Chancellor Hayden, criticizing Regents policy on standards
- Speeches. Regents Task Force on Teaching Speech 1998 (Box 26, Folder 27)
  Overview of major issues in the Regents Task Force on Teaching Report, with handwritten annotations, July 16, 1998
- Speeches. RA Speech Outline 1998 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  Handwritten and draft outline criticizing Regents policy on standards; memos and background information
- Speeches. RA Speech 1995 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  Draft with handwritten edits
- Speeches. RA Speech 1991 (Box 26, Folder 30)
  Text of speech; handwritten notes
- Speeches. Rally Speech, n.d (Box 26, Folder 31)
  Index cards with handwritten notes
- Speeches. NYSUT Retiree Issues 1988 (Box 26, Folder 32)
  Handwritten notes; background materials
- Speeches. Stress Speech Material 1979 (Box 26, Folder 33)
  Handwritten notes; NYSUT teacher survey re stress; related articles
- Speeches. Lessons for Life 1996 (Box 26, Folder 34)
  Agenda for NYSUT Lessons for Life training sessions; "Talking Points, Useful Facts, and Helpful Hints on the Bill of Rights and Responsibilities"; Hart Research survey, "Academic Standards and Student Discipline: AFT Teachers Assess Their Schools," 1995; newspaper clippings; handwritten notes
- Speeches. Mid. Country CSD, Centereach HS, Standards Speech 11/5/96, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 35)
  Materials re curriculum and assessment; newspaper clippings
- Speeches. Yorktown CSD, Yorktown HS, Standards Speech 10/10/97, 1997 (Box 26, Folder 36)
  Outline of speech; letter to Cortese from Yorktown Congress of Teachers; "Report of the Standards Committee to the Board of Education of Yorktown Central School District," August 1995; memo to Cortese from NYSUT associate Pat Flynn comparing Yorktown report to AFT criteria; talking points for Commissioner Mills' news conference, September 8, 1997; State Education Department Discussion Item re proposal for revising graduation requirements, September 12, 1997; NYSUT summary of the Commissioner's proposal on graduation requirements
- Staff Development 1983-1994 (Box 26, Folder 37)
  NYSUT Proposal for Training Conferences, January 1988; "Comprehensive Staff Development 1984-1985," interim evaluation report, January 1985; draft, "A Professional Development Committee in Every School District," 1994; memo, handwritten notes, and related materials. See also: Professional Development
- STANDARDS AND ASSESSMENT: (Box 26)
  Section includes standards for both teachers and students; See also: (Task Force to Study the) Preparation and Licensure of School Administrators and Supervisors; See also: Editorial Board Meetings; See also: Elementary School Standards; See also: Opportunity to Learn. Regents Temporary Ad Hoc Committee on Curriculum and Assessment; See also: Performance
  - AFT Meeting (Standards), September-October 2003 (Box 26, Folder 38)